Guide to the Hervey Allen Papers, 1831-1965 SC.1952.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Hervey Allen Papers
1831-1965
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Allen, Hervey
SC.1952.01
90 Linear Feet (185 manuscript boxes, 9 oversized boxes; 194 boxes total)
Hervey Allen was an American poet, essayist, and novelist. A University of Pittsburgh Alumnus (1915), Allen grew up in Pittsburgh. His paternal grandfather, Edward Jay Allen, was a Civil War Colonel and influential Pittsburgh figure who traveled west over the Oregon Trail to survey and establish United States land claim in 1852 in what is now Washington and Oregon. The papers primarily document the writing, publishing, and producing of Allen's literary works. They include manuscripts and notes, contracts with publishers and producers, proofs, correspondence with editors and readers, illustrations, and published works. Also present are family papers which include personal materials such as correspondence, diaries, genealogical research, journals, newspaper clippings, photographs, and scrapbooks from multi-generations of the Allen family. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically within the finding aid.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following ten series:
Series I. Early Life, Education, Military and Academic Careers, 1890-1949
Series II. Manuscripts, 1900-1949
Series III. Published Material, 1919-1945
Series IV. Prose and Press About, 1920-1959
Series V. General Correspondence, 1903-1972
Series VI: Literary Correspondence, 1916-1956
Series VII: Projects, 1932-1949
Series VIII: Estates and Financial Matters, 1919-1952
Series IX: Family Papers, 1831-1965
Series X: Oversized Material, 1856-1953
Biography
Hervey Allen was born William Hervey Allen Jr. in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, on December 8, 1889. Son of William Hervey Allen Sr. and Helen Eby Meyers Allen, Hervey Allen was one of five children. Allen spent much of his childhood at his grandfather's home, Edgehill, reading from his extensive personal library. Allen was educated in Shady Side Academy and at Pittsburgh Public Schools, graduating from high school in 1906.
In 1908 he went to Annapolis, Maryland, to attend Werntz, "a cramming school" to prepare for entrance to the United States Naval Academy. He was admitted in 1909 as a midshipman, but was discharged due to a stomach disorder in 1910. He returned to Pittsburgh and worked for the Bell Telephone Company. He then enrolled at the University of Pittsburgh's School of Economics in 1911, where he became a member of the Sigma Chi Fraternity. Allen graduated with Honors in 1915 with a Bachelor of Science in Economics.
He joined the National Guard with the 18th Pennsylvania Infantry, earning the rank of 2nd Lieutenant in 1916. His regiment was ordered to the Mexican border near El Paso, Texas, by President Wilson during the Mexican Expedition, where he wrote and published his first collection of poetry, Ballads of the Border.
Immediately upon his return, Allen was called to report to service for World War I on April 13, 1917. Allen was promoted to 1st Lieutenant of the 111th Infantry A.E.F. and spent the summer of 1917 guarding railroads in Western Pennsylvania. During the autumn of 1917, he went to Camp Hancock in Augusta, Georgia, for training with the 28th Pennsylvania Division. He deployed for France on April 30, 1918 aboard the Finland via New York. While at the front, Allen endured heavy fighting between the Marne and the Vasle. After the death of his captain at Fismette, he became Commander of Company B. He was seriously wounded there and was hospitalized on August 11, 1918. Upon his release, he served as an English instructor at the French Military Mission at Favernay. He was in Paris when the Armistice was signed. While at war, Hervey Allen wrote extensively and kept a diary of his experiences. From these writings Allen produced his most successful poem, The Blindman. His writings while at war inspired later works of his such as Toward the Flame and "It Was Like This: Two Stories of the Great War."
By the spring of 1919, Allen had been honorably discharged at Cap Dix, New Jersey. He settled in Charleston, South Carolina, to teach English, History, and Military Drill at the Porter Military Academy. With the exception of attending a summer English course at Harvard University in 1921, Allen remained in South Carolina, teaching at Charleston High School until 1924. While in South Carolina, he was influential in the revival of southern poetry, founding the Poetry Society of South Carolina with DuBose Heyward and others. By 1921, Allen had published two major poetry collections, Wampum and Old Gold and Carolina Chansons, Legends of the Low Country, a joint publication with Heyward.
Between 1924-1925, Allen was an English Instructor at Columbia University. By the latter half of 1925, Allen left Columbia to lecture American Literature at Vassar College. At Vassar, he met Annette Hyde Andrews, a student 18 years his junior whom he married in June 1927. During this time, Allen conducted extensive research on Edgar Allan Poe and published two separate works in 1926: Israfel: The Life and Times of Edgar Allan Poe and Poe's Brother: The Poems of William Henry Leonard Poe, a collaboration with Thomas Ollive Mabbott. Allen also published a collection of poems entitled, Earth Moods and Other Poems, and Toward the Flame, a novel based on his diary at war.
From 1927 to 1932 Hervey and Ann Allen lived in Bermuda at Felicity Hall, a plantation in Somerset, Parish of Sandys. While in Bermuda, Allen published several poems and collections including Sarah Simon and New Legends both published in 1929. In May of that same year, he began to write Anthony Adverse, the massively successful historical novel set during the Napoleonic era telling a man's journey across several continents in search of meaning to his life. Allen left Bermuda to complete and publish the novel in the United States in 1933. Anthony Adverse became Allen's most successful book, topping the Bestseller list in 1933 and 1934. The novel sold over 3 million copies, was translated in 13 different languages, and became a motion picture produced by Warner Bros. and directed by Mervyn LeRoy. The film starred Fredric March, Olivia de Haviland and Claude Rains, and earned several Academy Award nominations including Best Picture.
After the publication of Anthony Adverse, Allen devoted himself entirely to prose. The Allens settled at Bonfield, a plantation on the Eastern Shore of Maryland and remained there until the start of World War II. By 1938, Allen had written Action at Aquila, a historical novel about the Civil War and "It Was Like This: Two Stories of the Great War," in 1940.
In 1943, following the death of Stephen Vincent Benét, Allen was appointed as co-editor to Farrar & Rinehart's Rivers of America series. Together with Carl Carmer, Allen reviewed manuscript submissions dedicated to the history of individual American rivers. Also in 1943, Allen was appointed by President Roosevelt to join the War Manpower Commission as a Regional Information Representative in Atlanta, Georgia. Despite these commitments, Allen continued to write and set out to begin his most ambitious literary project: a five part volume on American history starting with Forest and the Fort, published in 1943, Bedford Village in 1944, and Toward the Morning in 1948. These three titles, though published individually, consisted of the first volume, The City and the Dawn, of the series, The Disinherited. Allen was working on Richfield Springs, the fourth and final installment of The City and the Dawn, when he suffered a fatal heart attack in The Glades, his Coconut Grove, Florida home on December 28th, 1949. He was survived by his wife Ann and their three children, Marcia, Mary Ann, and Richard. He is buried at Arlington National Cemetery.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Hervey Allen Papers, 1831-1965, SC.1952.01, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Acquisition Information
Portions of the papers were purchased from the estate of Hervey Allen (Mrs. Hervey Allen) in February 1952. Subsequent materials were donated through Holt, Rinehart and Winston publishing (formerly Farrar & Rinehart and Rinehart & Company) in 1964-1965 and Lawrence Kunetka of J & S Graphics in 1969.
Scope and Content Notes
The papers consist of handwritten, holograph and typewritten drafts and manuscripts, research notes, singular serial publications, and associated material related to press coverage of Allen's novels and film adaptations. Extensive personal and professional correspondence exists with Allen's main publishing company, Farrar & Rinehart/Rinehart & Company, and other international publishers; financial and business correspondence related to his personal and professional finances; and personal correspondence with notable writers such as Stephen Vincent Benét, William Rose Benét, John Bennett, Carl Carmer, Padraic Colum, John Drinkwater, Robert Frost, DuBose Heyward, Amy Lowell, Kenneth Roberts, E.A. Robinson and Philip Wylie.
Also present are the Allen's family papers which include correspondence, diaries, genealogical research, journals, newspaper clippings, photographs, and scrapbooks. Of special interest are the papers of this grandfather, Edward J. Allen, a Civil War Colonel and early pioneer of the Pacific Northwest territory and Allen's two great uncles, William H. and George T. Allen, both of whom document their involvement in Ohio and Mississippi riverboat activities.
Poets, American -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Poets, American -- 20th century; Authors, American -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Authors, American -- 20th century; Personal papers; Manuscripts for publication; Correspondence; Family papers; Financial records; Oregon National Historic Trail -- History; West (U.S.) -- History -- 19th century; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 -- Fiction; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; World War, 1914-1918; St. John's College (Annapolis, Md.); Bread Loaf School of English (Middlebury College); Bread Loaf Writers' Conference of Middlebury College; University of Pittsburgh -- Alumni and alumnae; Farrar, John Chipman; Allen, Edward Jay; Allen, Edward Jay -- Diaries; Benét, William Rose; Wyeth, Andrew; Lowell, Amy; Frost, Robert; Butcher, Fanny; Benét, Stephen Vincent; Allen family; Alexander, John White; Farrar & Rinehart; Allen, Hervey -- Alumni and alumnae; Rinehart & Company, Inc; United States. War Manpower Commission
- Early Life, Education, Military and Academic Careers, 1890-1949; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series includes material related to Hervey Allen's early life in Pittsburgh. Some materials included are ephemeral materials from his childhood, his paramilitary involvement with the Hiland Cadets and the US Naval Academy, his military papers during his service in World War I, and his years as an academic instructor in Charleston, South Carolina and New York.
  See Also
  For related oversized material, please see Oversized Materials series Box 189-190.
  - Early Life and Education, 1890-1949; 1.
    This first subseries includes material from Hervey Allen's childhood years, paramilitary activities, and education, including his involvement with the Hiland Cadets of which he was a part of in his teenage years. The "Ideal Scrapbook," a scrapbook Allen maintained while at the Naval Academy in his early twenties, features collected letters, photographs, drawings, and some early amateur writtings. Also featured are correspondence and associated materials Allen maintained with the University of Pittsburgh and the Sigma Chi fraternity. Notes he maintained for an English course he took at Harvard University are also featured.
    Please note: some photographs are included in this subseries, however, duplicates of these and the bulk of photographs can be found in Box 175. In addition, related material can be found in Boxes 189-190.
    - Birth Announcement, Baby Photographs, and Juvenilia, 1890-1896 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Cadet, A Monthly Publication of The Highland Presbyterian Boys Brigade, 1908-1915 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - U.S. Naval Academy Ideal Scrapbook, 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - U.S. Naval Academy Ideal Scrapbook (Loose Leaf Material), 1909-1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Pittsburgh University (University of Pittsburgh), 1913-1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Pittsburgh University (University of Pittsburgh), 1919-1949 (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
    - Sigma Chi Fraternity, 1912-1949 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
    - Harvard University English Course Material, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Military, 1916-1935; 2.
    This subseries chronicles Allen's military career, from his involvement with the Pennsylvania National Guard at the Mexican Border in 1916 to his deployment with the American Expeditionary Forces to France during World War I, to his Veteran Benefits documents. Allen's development as a writer is evidenced in his correspondence to his family during his military tours. In his August 5, 1918 letter to his aunt Mae he writes about the daily gross casualties at the "thick of war" and mentions, "I have some grand poems coming along." His observations and his growing disenchantment with the notion of war are evident in his notebook and letter writing from which Allen gathered much inspiration for his later works. Paricularly, his August 17, 1918 letter is written in a lucid narrative that later inspired Toward the Flame.
    Included in this subseries are correspondence, early writtings, official military papers, photographs, and an early will written while Allen was at the French front dated June 10, 1918.
    For more photographs taken by Hervey Allen while at the Mexican Border in Ysleta, Texas please see Box 178, Folder 6.
    Related items, such as Allen's combat uniform, oversized photographs, and honorary flags can be found in "Military Ephemera," Box 190, Series XI: Oversized Materials.
    - Letters Sent to Family at the Mexican Border, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Also includes letters sent from Camp Hancock in Augusta, Georgia while he was in the 28th Pennsylvania Division receiving training in preparation for World War I deployment to France during the autumn of 1917.
    - Photographs from the Mexican Border, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Other Finding Aids
      Box 178, Folder 6 for more photographs.
    - Letters Sent to Family (pre-WWI Deployment), 1918 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Letters Sent to Family (post-WWI Deployment), 1918 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Military Papers, 1918-1920 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    - Khaki WWI Notebook of Poetry, Letters, and Will, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - Veteran Benefits Documents, 1922-1935 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Academic and Teaching Career, 1919-1946; 3.
    The subseries contains lesson plans, related correspondence, exams, and various assignments from Allen's stint as an academic instructor at Porter Military Academy and Charleston High School, South Carolina and at Columbia University and Vassar College in New York.
    - Porter Military Academy: Correspondence, [Undated] (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Porter Military Academy: Correspondence, 1919-1935 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Porter Military Academy: Classroom Materials, 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Porter Military Academy: Course Outlines, 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Porter Military Academy: Assignments, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
    - Porter Military Academy: Assignments, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Porter Military Academy: Papers, 1919-1921 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Charleston High School: Correspondence, 1921-1925 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Charleston High School: First Term Notebook, 1921-1922 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Charleston High School: Examinations, 1923-1926 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Charleston High School: Course Materials, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Charleston Notebook, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Columbia University: Correspondence, 1923-1938 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Vassar College: Correspondence, 1925-1946 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
- Manuscripts, 1900-1949; II.
  This series includes all of Allen's manuscript iterative drafts, notes, revisions, editions, and some correspondence related to research and manuscript production. The subseries are arranged according to title and genre (Poetry and Prose), as well as incomplete or unpublished material.
  Oversized galleys of Allen's pre-published material are separately housed and can be found in Series XI: Oversized Material, Box 187-188.
  - Poetry, 1900-1949; 1.
    This subseries contains early handwritten and typewritten rough drafts of mostly subsequently published poems. The first subseries features Allen's draft single leaf titles, the second subseries features collective manuscript material of Allen's major poems and collections, and the third features poetry written by other authors. Because many of the materials lack dates in particular the single title materials, titles are arranged alphabetically. Some materials lack a proper titles or have indecipherable titles. For these, titles with ellipses reflect indecipherable or illegible words or phrases. For materials without a clear given title, titles are borrowed from the first discernable verse of the poem and are in brackets.
    - Single Titles
      - Single Titles: A (Box 5, Folder 1)
        - After the March: Nogent l'Artaud, 1918; 1.
        - Afterglow, 1931; 2.
        - Aftermath, 1920; 3.
        - Alchemy, 4.
        - [All are snowcapped mountains…], 1900; 5.
        - Amelia Burr: A Ballad of Old Charleston, 6.
        - America's First First, 7.
        - [And now he dwells…], 8.
        - Anodyne, 9.
        - The Answer, 1917-1925; 10.
        - Any Time, 11.
        - The Apple Tree, 12.
        - An Approach to An Epitaph, 13.
        - Analia Felix, 14.
        - As It Was In The Beginning, 15.
        - Assama, 16.
        - At Alcantara, 17.
        - [At Azerbaijain in the lakes of Khar…], 1949; 18.
        - Autumn, 1918; 19.
        - Autumn Invocation: The Seasons Wait Their Turns Among the Stars, 20.
        - Autumn Portents, 21.
      - Single Titles: B (Box 5, Folder 2)
        - Bacchus Is Gone, 1.
        - Back River, 2.
        - [Bad the time and the bee…], 3.
        - Ballad of Death Romance, 4.
        - Ballad of the Fruitless Plant, 5.
        - Banished, 6.
        - Baskets, 7.
        - Beaumont, 1918; 8.
        - Beauty and Love, 1916; 9.
        - [The bees once fell a quarreling on the couch…], 10.
        - Bermuda, 11.
        - Bewitched: An Incident from the Life of Pierre Loti, 12.
        - Beyond Debate, 13.
        - Beyond the Night, 1916; 14.
        - Bibles, 15.
        - Big Bend, 16.
        - Big Cove, 17.
        - Bill, 1918; 18.
        - Biography and Epitaph of Verbum Sap, 19.
        - The Blindman: A Ballad of Nogent l'Artaud, 1918-1919; 20.
        - The Blockade Runner, 21.
        - Bright Star, 22.
        - Burnt Sons, 1945; 23.
        - Business, 24.
      - Single Titles: C (Box 5, Folder 3)
        - The Cat Man, 1.
        - The Cat Witch, 1926; 2.
        - The Children by the Lake of Dreams: A Persian Fragment, 1930; 3.
        - Christmas Coloure, 4.
        - Christmas Magic, 5.
        - [Clear as the burning heart of love…], 6.
        - Clio, 7.
        - La Clouche Joyeuse, 8.
        - Les Cloches, 9.
        - Confession, 10.
        - Considerations: After the Fight at Croix Rouge Farm, 11.
        - Conversation in Morningside, 12.
      - Single Titles: D (Box 5, Folder 4)
        - The Dark Tower, 1916; 1.
        - Dark Tower by Night, 2.
        - Day Star, 3.
        - Death of the Elk, 4.
        - Dem Boids: A Ballad of the Bronx, 5.
        - [Dedicated to the man...], 6.
        - [Democracy, the bastard bitch...], 7.
        - Despair, 8.
        - Diana of the Dunes, 1925; 9.
        - [Debbie] Song, 10.
        - [The difficulty of making songs...], 11.
        - Dirge, 12.
        - Dog Days, 13.
        - [The dog in the manger...], 14.
        - Doomed, 15.
        - Dragon's Breath, 16.
        - Dream Flowers, 17.
        - Dream Fragment, 1920; 18.
        - Dream Friend, 19.
        - The Dream Wood, 20.
        - Dull Days, 21.
        - Dust, 22.
      - Single Titles: E (Box 5, Folder 5)
        - Easter, 1918; 1.
        - Echoes, 1915; 2.
        - Eclipse, 3.
        - El Paso, 1916; 4.
        - Elesmir, 5.
        - Encore un Autre, 1919; 6.
        - L'envoi, 7.
        - Epilogue, 8.
        - Eventide, 9.
      - Single Titles: F (Box 5, Folder 6)
        - Fable of the Dog and Cat, 1.
        - Fall, 2.
        - First Love, 3.
        - Fleur de Lis, 4.
        - [The flood of May has moved into June...], 5.
        - For Annette's Andirons, 6.
        - For DuBose Heyward, 1940; 7.
        - [For though from gentle Jennifer...], 8.
        - Forest Whisperers, 9.
        - Friendship, 10.
        - Four Proverbs of Hell, 11.
      - Single Titles: G (Box 5, Folder 7)
        - Gamesters All, 1.
        - Gemini, 2.
        - General Court Martial, 1919; 3.
        - Goat Song, 4.
        - [Goat of the [farther] left of old...], 5.
        - Goin' Home?, 6.
        - Going to Bed, 7.
        - The Gold Star, 1916; 8.
        - The Golden Ghost, 9.
        - Goodbye Sweet Day, 10.
        - The Goose Creek Voice, 11.
        - [The great [anthological] with front of brass…], 12.
        - The Great Right Whale: A Fisherman's Prayer, 1947; 13.
      - Single Titles: H (Box 5, Folder 8)
        - Hadrian at Tivoli, 1.
        - Hag Hollerin' Time, 2.
        - [Hail bright [magical brat]...], 3.
        - Hail Columbia, 4.
        - Hands Off! Dedicated to Orators and Others, 5.
        - Hark, 6.
        - Headlines, 7.
        - Helen, 8.
        - Hermitage, 9.
        - A Hermitage of Bells: A Fantasy, 10.
        - Hiking, 1916; 11.
        - The Holy Rood: A Chant, 12.
        - Horoscope for A.A.A., 13.
        - The Hours of Childhood, 14.
        - [How did the archaeopteryx…], 15.
        - The House by the Marsh, 1929; 16.
        - How Long, 17.
        - [How to propose none of us C…], 18.
        - Human Hands, 19.
        - Hylas, 20.
        - A Hymn on Christmas Morning, 21.
        - Hymn to Time, 22.
      - Single Titles: I (Box 5, Folder 9)
        - [I think some dusk [they] metal [mice]…], 1.
        - Illegitimate, 1925; 2.
        - In Dear Old Fashion '89, 3.
        - In Memoriam: Major Christopher Magee Anderson, Eighteenth Pennsylvania Infantry, 1916; 4.
        - In the Woods, 5.
        - Inspiration, 6.
        - [Into these dark pastures...], 7.
        - Isis, 8.
        - Island Winter: Lat. 31 [degrees] N, 9.
      - Single Titles: J (Box 5, Folder 10)
        - Jewish Bonds and Genital [Reviews], 1.
        - John Brashear, 2.
        - June, 3.
        - Jungle Night: To Ann's Bronze Elephants, 4.
      - Single Titles: K (Box 5, Folder 11)
        - The Kettle-Mending at La Luz, 1.
        - King Agog's Bed, 2.
      - Single Titles: L (Box 5, Folder 12)
        - La Fayette Lands, 1.
        - Landbound, 2.
        - The Last Crew, 3.
        - The Latter Day Saint, 4.
        - Light on the Hills, 5.
        - The Little One at Home, 1916; 6.
        - [The little poets of our great despair...], 7.
        - Locusts, 1917; 8.
        - [Lumerary], 9.
        - Lust, 10.
        - The Lute, 1919; 11.
      - Single Titles: M (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - Macabre in Macaws, 1.
        - Madonna, 2.
        - The Mainspring, 3.
        - Major Andre's Flute and Shelley's Skylark, 4.
        - Manhattan Matins, 5.
        - Marcia's May-Day Song, 6.
        - The Marshland, 1919; 7.
        - Melpomeme's Song, 8.
        - Middleton's Gardens, 9.